Guide to the Records of Town Hall RG.37.25
New York University Archives
Records of Town Hall
circa 1846-1985
1930-1978
New York University Archives
League for Political Education (U.S.)
Town Hall, Inc.
RG.37.25
25.77 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes, 5 flat boxes, 10 oversized flat boxes, and 6 record cartons
The Town Hall, a musical venue in New York City, has its roots in late 19th century political activism. Founded as the League for Political Education, the Town Hall served primarily as a forum for political speakers in the early 20th century before shifting focus to performance midcentury. It merged with NYU in 1958 and remained under the university's control until 1978. Its records contain administrative and legal files, photographs, event programs and publications including newsletters and volumes dedicated to prominent individuals. Outside publications related to the League for Political Education's founders are included as are documents relating to the merger with NYU.
Separated Materials note
Photographs of Town Hall have been removed to New York University Archives' photo collection under Non-NYU Subjects.
Conditions Governing Access
Certain items in this collection are fragile and may require special handling or intervention from archives staff.
Contact the University Archives for specific access restrictions.
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Scope and Contents note
The administrative series in this collection contains files on Town Hall's buildings as well as some budget and fundraising material. The collection includes legal correspondence and papers such certificates of occupancy, trademark, mortgage and tax documents. A variety of programs from more than 70 years of lectures and performances held at Town Hall are included in this collection. It also contains photographs of Town Hall performers and early members, and clippings and internally produced materials related to the history of the organization. The Town Hall disseminated several publications including a newsletter, The Town Crier; Enduring Names, biographies of notable individuals who had endowed lecture series at Town Hall; and other promotional publications. Issues of these publications can be found in the collection. Correspondence from Town Hall Director Lawrence Zucker from 1981 to 1985, audio reels of lectures, and bound biographies of League of Political Education founders are included in the papers as well.
The collection also includes four scrapbooks. Two contain materials related to the production of "America's Town Meeting of the Air," a political forum broadcasted from Town Hall for more than 20 years, the third is comprised of membership materials and the fourth contains League of Political Education material from the beginning of the 20th century.
Some materials relate to events, such as "America's Town Meeting of the Air." They also address topics including Town Hall's 1958 merger with NYU, the purchase of 123 West 43rd Street and the purchase and sale of the adjacent Town Hall Annex and construction projects.
Notes related to a 1978 survey of the collection that were found among the Town Hall papers have been included in this collection. They are in Series VIII - Related Materials.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into nine series: Administrative files; Legal files; Publications; Programs; Clippings; Portraits/photographs; Audiovisual; Related materials; Oversize material. The Programs series has been divided into three subseries: Town Hall Opening; Lectures/courses; Performance.
Original order was maintained in the Administrative files and Legal files series. These series were extant when the University Archives received the collection and were largely kept intact. Materials belonging in the other series were removed and placed within the appropriate series. The order of the files in these series was preserved from a previous arrangement. The seven other series were culled from the entirety of the collection and were derived from a reorganization of the material.
Programs and Clippings are arranged chronologically. Portraits/photographs are arranged alphabetically.
Original order was maintained in the Administrative files and Legal files series. These series were extant when the University Archives received the collection and were largely kept intact. Materials belonging in the other series were removed and placed within the appropriate series. The order of the files in these series was preserved from a previous arrangement. The seven other series were culled from the entirety of the collection and were derived from a reorganization of the material.
Programs and clippings are arranged chronologically. Portraits/photographs are arranged alphabetically.
This collection has been arranged into nine series:
Missing Title
Series I: Administrative Files
Series II: Legal Files
Series III: Publications
Series IV: Programs
Series V: Clippings
Series VI: Portraits/Photographs
Series VII: Audiovisual
Series VIII: Related Materials
Series IX: Oversize Materials
The Programs series has been divided into three subseries: Town Hall Opening; Lectures/courses; Performance.
Historical Note
The Town Hall Inc. was organized as the League for Political Education in 1894 by six prominent New York women after a suffrage measure was defeated in the New York State Legislature. The purpose of the league was to educate the public about the issue by holding educational programs and lectures. The events were held at small rented venues. The League for Political Education gave birth to offshoot groups such as the Economic Club and Civic Forum. In 1904 the League became incorporated and changed its name to the Board of Trustees of the League for Political Education.
The building of an auditorium for the League for Political Education began in 1919 as the organization outgrew its small venues and sought a permanent home. The structure, which also included office space, was designed by architecture firm McKim, Mead and White. It opened January 1921 at 123 W. 43rd Street. It was dubbed the Town Meeting Hall.
Soon after the doors opened to lecturers and audiences, it was realized the auditorium had exceptional acoustics. And so the Town Meeting Hall became a venue for musical performance as well as political expression. Independent groups such as the New York University Club also rented space from the organization.
In 1930 the League for Political Education purchased the adjacent the building at 125 W. 43rd Street for its Town Hall Annex for more space. It subsequently sold the building in 1959. The league began hosting and broadcasting its "America's Town Meeting of the Air" radio lecture series in 1935. The series ran until 1956 and provided a forum for political and cultural experts to discuss current events issues.
The organization changed its name to The Town Hall, Inc. in 1937 to reflect its expanding programming. In the late 1950s Town Hall experienced a decline. It merged with New York University in 1958 and came under the jurisdiction of the Division of General Education (now the School of Continuing Education) until 1978 when the university divested itself from the organization.
Town Hall remains primarily a musical venue focusing on jazz and arts education.
Provenance
This collection was transferred by Dorothy Swanson, Head of Special Collections at Elmer Holmes Bobst Library.
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Archival material about Town Hall can also be found in Administrative Files of the Dean of the School of Education, Daniel E. Griffiths, RG 26.0.1.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Adult education; America's town meeting of the air (Radio program).; Architectural drawings (visual works); Audiotapes.; Auditoriums.; Awards; Books.; Brochures.; Bylaws (administrative records); Certificates of occupancy.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Entertainers.; Lectures and lecturing.; Legal documents.; Music-halls.; Musical performance.; Newsletters.; Pamphlets.; Political activists.; Radio addresses, debates, etc.; Registers (lists).; Scrapbooks.; Stats (copies).; Women political activists.; Photographs.; Budgets.; Baldwin, James, 1924-1987; Fielde, Adele M. (Adele Marion); Gregory, Dick; Hatfield, Mark O., 1922-; Jacobi, Mary Putnam, 1842-1906; League for Political Education (U.S.); Nader, Ralph; New York University. Division of General Education; New York University. School of Continuing Education; Town Hall, Inc.; Voznesenskii, Andrei, 1933-2010
- Series I - Administrative Files, 1913-1985; 1951-1977
  Scope and Contents note
  The folders in this series are in keeping with the original order established by a prior arrangement. Their contents were left largely intact as well. Items were removed and placed in other series once the other series were established.
  - Annex, Purchase and Administration of, 1929-59 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appraisal, 1951-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees, 1951-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Budget and Expense Reports, 1956-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Building Files: Building plans and proposed renovations, 1913-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Corporations and Business - Prospect Evaluation List of Prospects, undated (Box 1, File 6)
  - Correspondence: Director Larry Zucker - Fireguard, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Director Larry Zucker - Pieper New York-Multistate Bar Review, Ltd., 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Director Larry Zucker - International Paper Company, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Director Larry Zucker - Misc., 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fundraising reports and promotional material, 1924-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - History of Town Hall, 1919-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - New York Public Library (Disposition of Records), 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Survey, Analysis and Plan of Fund-Raising for the League for Political Education, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Events: America's Town Meeting of the Air, 1943-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Events: Preview at Town Hall, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Events: The University Awards, 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Events: Misc., 1971, 1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series II - Legal Files, 1904-1964
  The folders in this series were maintained from a previous arrangement.
  - Sale of Town Hall Annex, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cadwater, Wickersham & Taft (attorneys), 1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Certificate of Incorporation and Bylaws of League for Political Education, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Certificate of Incorporation and Bylaws of Town Hall, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Nordlinger, Riegelman, Benetar & Charney (attorneys), 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Mortgage (2nd), 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ownership of Town Hall (Certificate of Occupancy), 1925 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Consolidation and Merger with NYU, 1956-1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Tax Situation, 1943-1958 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Trademarks, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series III - Publications, 1922-1954, undated
  - America's Town Meeting of the Air, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Town Meeting: Bulletin of America's Town Meeting of the Air - Vol. IV nos. 1-13, 14-26, 1938, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Town Meeting: Bulletin of America's Town Meeting of the Air - Vol. V nos. 1-13, Vol. VI nos. 1-13, 1939, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Town Meeting: Bulletin of America's Town Meeting of the Air - Vol. IX nos. 26-51, Vol. XV nos. 1-26, 1943, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Town Crier (various issues), 1930-1936 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The Town Hall (various publications), 1922, 1930, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940, 1946, 1953, 1954, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series IV - Programs, 1912-1986
  - Subseries A. Town Hall Opening, 1920-1924
    - Programs related to opening of Town Hall, 1920-1924 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Subseries B. Lectures/Courses, 1914-1974
    - Lectures/Courses, 1912-1974 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Undated programs (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Subseries C. Performance, 1938-1986
    - Performance programs, 1938-1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Undated programs (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series V - Clippings, circa 1920-1976
  This series consists of two folders with clippings about news events in 1963 in which Town Hall played a role: a riot outside Town Hall after students who traveled to Cuba spoke to an audience at the hall; the Birmingham, Alabama church bombing that killed four African-American girls, in response to which Town Hall held a fundraiser featuring James Baldwin. The third folder is comprised of clippings that were located all over the collection.
  - Anti-Castro protest outside Town Hall, 1963 September (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Birmingham, Alabama church bombing, 1963 September (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1920-1977, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series VI - Portraits/Photographs, circa 1846-1978
  Photographic portraits were gathered from among the entire collection. This series contains autographed portraits of singers, musicians and dancers who performed at Town Hall. It also includes portraits of the founders and early members of The League for Political Education, which would become The Town Hall in 1938. These include Dr. Mary Putnam Jacobi, Eleanor Butler Sanders, Lee Wood Haggin, Catherine A. B. Abbe, Lucia Gilbert Runkle, Edwin Denison Morgan, Josephine MacLeod, and Adele M. Fielde.
  - Edwin Denison Morgan, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Josephine MacLeod, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Portraits A-E, approximately 1846, approximately 1856, 1969, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 3-5)
  - Portraits F-M, 1911-1914, undated (Box 6, Folder 6-8)
  - Portraits N-Z, 1971-1972, undated (Box 27, Folder 1-4)
  - Unidentified portraits, undated (Box 27, Folder 5-6)
  - Founders portraits, circa 1900s (Box 27, Folder 7)
- Series VII - Audiovisual, 1971
  - Dick Gregory - 1 of 3, 1971 April 22; cuid17980 (Box 7, Reel 1)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Duration: 55 minutes
  - Dick Gregory - 2 of 3, 1971 April 22; cuid17981 (Box 7, Reel 2)
    Duration: 52 minutes
  - Dick Gregory - 3 of 3, 1971 April 22; cuid17982 (Box 7, Reel 3)
  - Ralph Nader - 1 of 1, 1971 March 4; cuid17983; Distinguished Speaker Series #1 (Box 7, Reel 4)
    Duration: 103 minutes
  - Andrei Voznesenskii, Soviet Poet - 1 of 4, 1971 November 10; cuid17984 (Box 7, Reel 5)
    Duration: 34 minutes
  - Andrei Voznesenskii, Soviet Poet - 2 of 4, 1971 November 10; cuid17985 (Box 7, Reel 6)
    Duration: 32 minutes
  - Andrei Voznesenskii, Soviet Poet - 3 of 4, 1971 November 10; cuid17986 (Box 7, Reel 7)
    Duration: 33 minutes
  - Andrei Voznesenskii, Soviet Poet - 4 of 4, 1971 November 10; cuid17987 (Box 7, Reel 8)
    Duration: 9 minutes
  - Sen. Mark O. Hatfield, 1971 May 11; cuid17988 (Box 7, Reel 9)
    Duration: 71 minutes
- Series VIII - Related Materials, 1916-1978
  - Preliminary inventory of collection, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Radio Guide award, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Elgin R. L. Gould: A Memorial, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Memorial Biography of Adele M. Fielde (3 copies), 1918 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    General note
    The third copy of this book is in folder 5.
  - Life and Letters of Mary Putnam Jacobi, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Series IX - Oversize Materials, 1900-1904, 1931-1969, undated
  This series contains 14 large bound books and scrapbooks. It includes seven volumes of Enduring Names, one of which is unnumbered.
  - Enduring Names, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Enduring Names Volume 1, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Enduring Names Volume 2, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Enduring Names Volume 3, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Enduring Names Volume 4, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Enduring Names Volume 5, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Enduring Names Volume 6, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - New York University Club Visitors Register, 1958-1969 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Membership scrapbook, circa 1945-1946 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - America's Town Meeting of the Air scrapbook, circa 1937-1939 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - America's Town Meeting of the Air scrapbook, circa 1945 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - League for Political Education scrapbook, circa 1900-1904; cuid18137 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Crane Starkey and Allied Family Histories (2 copies), 1931 (Box 21, Folder 1)